Guide to the Camille Chautemps papers M1601
Stanford University. Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Series VI: Stavisky Affair
  - Stavisky Affair Clippings
    - "Deux importante depositions de MM. Pachot et Cousin ont fait eclater les responsabilites du conseiller Prince," L'Oeuvre, Nov. 26, 1935 (Flat-box 41, Folder 14)
- Series VII: Relevant Political and Historical Documents
  - Details of WWI Armistice, 1918 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Notes outlining events of 1940 (From 1941 National Year Book) (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Photocopies of gov't documents pertaining to collapse of France: Pétain, Hitler, Bordeaux government, Algeria, 1940 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Mission from Pétain to Chautemps, re: Latin America, 1940 (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Letter from S.E. De Souza Dantas, ex-Ambassador of Brazil in Paris, to Jean Chautemps clarifying that Camille Chautemps was not refused visa in 1940 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Dumesnil's "Ordre de mission:" Movement of gov't. to La Bourboule, June 25, 1940 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Letter to Maréchal Pétain by "Grad Orient" Freemasons, 1940 (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Weygand: Report on military situation and opinion on North Africa, June 1940 (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Letter from Bevan to Pomaret, re: British Expeditionary Force, May 1940 (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Letter from Claude Bowers to FDR, re: Europe, 1937 (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - Documents and correspondence re: Massilia (also, Jean Zay, Charles Pomaret) (Box 32, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence between William Bullitt and FDR, re: Europe (and Chautemps), 1936-1940 (Box 32, Folder 12)
  - Letters to US Secretary of State from "Biddle" re: French defeat June 16, 1940 (Box 32, Folder 13)
  - Maréchal Pétain: Accounts of end of war, 1944-45 (Box 32, Folder 14)
  - Short bio for L'Abbe Desgranges (1874-1958) (Box 32, Folder 15)
  - Marcel Saldeau, French Radical party politician: Account of his activities, 1936-1946 (Box 32, Folder 16)
  - Pamphlets: Edouard Daladier's "Reponse aux Chefs Communistes" and "Les Chefs Communistes Francais et la Guerre," 1946 (Box 32, Folder 17)
  - NYTimes Book Review: "The Abandonment of the Jews" by David S. Wyman, 1984 (Box 32, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous: Nov. 18, 1944, Ordonnance instituant une haute cour de justice (Box 32, Folder 19)
  - Photocopies of docs pertaining to Leca, Devaux, and Ambassadorship in Washington (Box 33, Folder 33)
  - Invitation, program to Truman inauguration, 1949 (Box 32, Folder 20)
  - Margaret Truman: Thank you letter to Mme. Chautemps for hat (Box 32, Folder 21)
  - Mrs. Eisenhower's invitation to Mme. Chautemps, 1948 (Box 32, Folder 22)
  - Pres. Carter inauguration guide, 1977 (Box 32, Folder 23)
  - Dinner program and Pres. Carter's speech from celebration of Egyptian-Israeli Peace Treaty, 1979 (Box 32, Folder 24)
  - Carter White House dinner program, 1981 (Box 32, Folder 25)
  - Christmas card from President Carter and First Lady (Box 32, Folder 26)
  - GOP sponsorship request from Pres. Reagan, 1984 (Box 32, Folder 27)
- Series VIII: Clippings
  - Clippings: "Felix Chautemps dans la guerre et sa morte," 1915 (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Misc. newspapers from 1917, 1918, 1919 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - "L'Allemagne a capitule: L'Armistice est signe," Le Matin, November 12, 1918 (Flat-box 40, Folder 12)
  - "La fete de la liberte du monde," Le Petit Journal, July 5, 1918 (Flat-box 40, Folder 13)
  - L'Exporteur Francais: La Grande Semaine de Tours, May 1922 (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Camille Chautemps: First nomination as minister, 1923 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Federation Nationale de la Mutualite et de la Cooperation Agricoles, 1924 (Speech by Chautemps, pp. 195-200) (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - 15th Congress of the Association of the Mayors of France: Banquet for Chautemps, 1924 (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - Journal Officiel: Debats Parlementaires, 1925 (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Radical Party Clippings, 1927 (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - La Depeche, Jan. 31, 1928 (see p.2, Chautemps reference in relation to Federation Republicaine, Radicale et Radicale-Socialiste) (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Parti Republicain Radical et Radical-Socialiste: Undated news report on meeting (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - Camille Chautemps: Clippings referencing him, 1930s (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - Clippings: Personal interest story on Chautemps at home in Blois, Vu et Lu magazine, late 1930's (Box 35, Folder 10)
  - Radical Party, acclamation for Camille Chautemps, 1932 (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Book of newspaper clippings from Dec. 10, 1933 (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - Journal Officiel: Debats Parlementaires (Chautemps, President du conseil, ministre de l'interieur), 1933 (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Chautemps clippings, President du Conseil, Ministre de l'Interieur, Nov. 1933 (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Debats Parlementaires ("Redressement finance"), 1933 (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - Death of Mme. Dimitrief in Chautemps' home, undated (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - Debat sur la politique exterieure, 1934 (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Jeunesses Republicaines Radicales et Radicales Socialistes de France, "L'heure de la Jeunesse," 1935 (Box 33, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, responses to Chautemps' call for "rapprochement des Francais," August 1936 (Box 33, Folder 11)
  - Discours a Angers by Chautemps, Oct. 1936 (Box 35, Folder 9)
  - Camille Chautemps: Clipping on reception for Canadian legion, 1936 (Box 33, Folder 12)
  - Report of speech delivered au congres du Loir-et-Cher de l'Union Nationale des Anciens Combattants, 1937 (Box 33, Folder 13)
  - Discours a la Federation radicale de Loir-et-Cher, 1937 (Box 35, Folder 11)
  - La Depeche ou Centre: M. le President Chautemps in Champigny-en-Beauce, 1938 (Box 35, Folder 12)
  - Journal Officiel: Debats Parlementaires, March 1938 (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Political cartoon on Chautemps: "Il est charmant!" (Box 33, Folder 14)
  - Blois notice of public auction of land and property (incl. one lot owned by Chautemps), 1939 (Box 35, Folder 13)
  - Copies of New York Times clipping refencing Chautemps, 1936-1940 (Box 35, Folder 16)
  - Vichy government Journal Oficiel: Lois et Decrets, July 1940 (Box 35, Folder 14)
  - Camille Chautemps' inclusion in Petain's first cabinet: clipping, June 1940 (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - Reports of Chautemps' arrival in US, Nov. 1940 (Box 35, Folder 15)
  - "Il y a un secret entre Weygand et Petain," by Reynaud, France-soir, July 14, 1941 (Flat-box 41, Folder 2)
  - De Gaulle on Free French and criticism of Chautemps, 1942 (Box 33, Folder 15)
  - Operation Chautemps-Frossard: news references, undated (also, Darlan 1942) (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - "Links Future of France to Friendly US: Chautemps in Call to 'Unite and Work,'" Des Moines Register, Sept. 4, 1944 (Flat-box 41, Folder 5)
  - Liberation of France: newspapers from September 1944 (Box 33, Folder 16)
  - "Les Dessous de L'Armistice: La Trahison de Bordeaux," L'Aurore, Sept. 11, 1944 (Flat-box 40, Folder 4)
  - Clippings from Le Figaro: retrospective of 1937-1938, dated 1978 (Box 33, Folder 17)
  - Elections legislatives du 21 Octobre: Parti Republicain Radical et Radical-Socialiste (signed by Nicole Abeille, Chautemps' daughter), 1945 (Box 36, Folder 11)
  - End of War, Pétain Trial: US newspaper clippings, 1945 (Box 35, Folder 17)
  - End of War, Pétain Trial: US newspaper clippings, 1945 (cont'd.) (Box 35, Folder 18)
  - End of War, Pétain trial clipping and Camille Chautemps' notes, 1945 (Box 35, Folder 19)
  - Reynaud accusations against Camille Chautemps, related clippings, 1945 (Box 35, Folder 20)
  - Camille Chautemps: Comments on Herriot's "Quinzaine Tragique" articles on Fall of France, 1945 (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - Proces du Marechal Petain, 1945 (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Clippings on Chautemps' past and potential return to France, 1945 (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - "Reynaud Brands Chautemps Guilty," by Reynaud, NYTimes, August 8, 1945 (with Chautemps' annotations) (Flat-box 41, Folder 3)
  - Ce Soir (front page only), Sept. 7-17, 1945 (Flat-box 40, Folder 8)
  - US clippings on verdict and trial in absentia, 1947 (Box 33, Folder 18)
  - Clippings referring back to Munich Crisis, 1947 (Box 33, Folder 19)
  - Clippings re: Chautemps' conviction in 1947 (Box 35, Folder 21)
  - Camille Chautemps: Clippings relating to condemnation in French press, 1947 (Box 36, Folder 9)
  - "Petain voulait demissionner le 16 Juin 40," by Reynaud, France-soir, June 7, 1947 (Flat-box 41, Folder 1)
  - "La flotte pouvait aller aux USA en juin 1940," by Reynaud, France-soir, June 9, 1947 (Flat-box 41, Folder 4)
  - André Frossard article, "Ils ne peuvent attendre que l'histoire revise leurs proces," 1948 (Box 36, Folder 12)
  - Camille Chautemps: Letter to Time/Life magazine protesting misrepresentation, 1948 (Box 33, Folder 20)
  - Camille Chautemps: Article in defense of, by Emile Bure in "L'ordre de Paris," 1948 (Box 33, Folder 21)
  - NYTimes on French cabinet crisis, 1948 (Box 35, Folder 22)
  - "By Winston Churchill: The Second World War," (Munich Winter), NYTimes, April 27, 1948 (Flat-box 40, Folder 7)
  - "Le Veritable Montoire: (Oct.11-24) L'entrevue Hitler-Petain" by Kammerer, May 8, 1948 (Flat-box 40, Folder 5)
  - "Les origines de la campagne de Tunisie (Nov. 1942)," by Kammerer, July 10, 1948 (Flat-box 40, Folder 2)
  - Banquet des "Mille," Association des Representants du Peuple de la Troisieme Republique, 1948 (Box 36, Folder 10)
  - "President Truman Takes Oath at Noon; Nation's Greatest Inaugural Celebration," NYTimes, Jan. 20, 1949 (Flat-box 40, Folder 9)
  - Truman's Inauguration, Washington Post, January 21, 1949 (Flat-box 40, Folder 10)
  - Truman's Inauguration, Washington Daily news, January 20-21, 1949 (Flat-box 40, Folder 11)
  - NYTimes obituary for Maurice Maeterlinck, 1949 (Box 36, Folder 13)
  - French Foreign Minister Schuman visits Chautemps in US (Box 33, Folder 22)
  - Le Figaro, "La deposition de Léon Blum devant la Commission d'Enquête," Dec. 1951 (Box 35, Folder 24)
  - "Les Chercheurs pas Curieux:" columnist criticizes investigative commission of 1933-1945 events, 1951 (Box 36, Folder 14)
  - Bulletin de la Ligue de la Republique: Discours de Georges Bonnet, 1951 (Box 36, Folder 15)
  - Bonnet speech: Injustice of the electoral laws on ineligibility, 1951(?) (Box 36, Folder 16)
  - "L'operation Chautemps-Frossard:" Le Figaro, Dec. 2, 1951 (Flat-box 40, Folder 1)
  - Aux Ecoutes article, "Camille Chautemps veut revenir pour etre juge," 1952 (Box 33, Folder 23)
  - Camille Chautemps' potential return to France, related clippings, 1945-1952 (Box 36, Folder 8)
  - Clippings from "L'Aurore" and others, retrospective of 1940, from 1952-1954 (Box 33, Folder 24)
  - Promotion of Louis Proust to Legion of Honor, 1954 (Box 36, Folder 18)
  - Camille Chautemps' return to France, related clipings, 1954 (Box 33, Folder 25)
  - Churchill, Rudolph. Article in Figaro accusing Chautemps of treason, 1954 (Box 33, Folder 26)
  - Clippings from Journal Officiel requested by C. Chautemps, 1954 (Box 33, Folder 27)
  - Camille Chautemps: Clippings and correspondence re: Lutetia speech, 1956 (Box 33, Folder 28)
  - Figaro Litteraire: "Comment meurt une republique" (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - "Les Erreurs Tragiques de la Guerre Contre Hitler," L'Express, April 21, 1960 (Flat-box 40, Folder 6)
  - C. Chautemps automobile accident clippings, 1956 (Box 36, Folder 22)
  - French Army Parade in Paris, program, 1958 (Box 36, Folder 19)
  - The Evening Sun, "Our Yesterdays: News of 1933 from the Evening Sun..." feature on Chautemps, 1958 (Box 33, Folder 29)
  - "L'interprete Paul Schmidt: Hitler offre a Petain d'entrer en guerre contre l'Angleterre," L'Aurore, Oct. 23, 1960 (Flat-box 40, Folder 3)
  - Chautemps responses to Pres. Eisenhower's support for de Gaulle's stance on Algeria (Box 33, Folder 30)
  - French press clippings on posthumous publication of "Cahiers Secrets de l'Armistice," 1963 (Box 33, Folder 31)
  - Chautemps obituaries, July 1963 (Box 35, Folder 25)
  - "A missed dealing," article on Chautemps by Charles Pomaret, 1970 (Box 33, Folder 32)
  - "Figaro," 1981 (p. 15 Griset article referencing Henri, Gerard Durand-Texte) (Box 39, Folder 15)
  - La Vie du Rail: Societe Nationale des Chemins de Fer Francais (SNCF), 1987 (Box 35, Folder 26)
  - Death of Trotsky's French bodyguard clipping (also, reference to Chautemps' grant of visa to Trotsky), undated (Box 33, Folder 34)
  - Paroles Francaises clipping, (p. 4 "Un siecle et demi d'opinions autorisees"- Chautemps quote) (Box 35, Folder 23)
  - Pamphlet by Jean Castagnez, Depute de Cher, outlining events leading to Vichy government of July 1940 (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Letter to "Le Monde" from Isorni re: President Paul-Boncour's support for Petain (Box 36, Folder 17)
  - Speech given by André Cornu as candidate for President of France (Box 36, Folder 20)
  - Op-Ed in English language newspaper: Pierre Mendes-France, "Monsieur Quixote" (Radical Party Prime Minister), undated (Box 36, Folder 21)
  - "L'Armistice a la lumiere de Documents Recents," by Louis Rougier, undated (Box 36, Folder 23)
  - Camille Chautemps: Clippings from US lecture tours (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Camille Chautemps: Clippings from US lecture tours (incl. details and expenses) (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Misc. clippings (Box 36, Folder 24)
- Series IX: Media: Seven phonograph albums, unknown content. Some are marked "Piano Solos" and "Ravel," but most are unmarked. (Oversize-box 42)